All right.
Great.
So hi, everybody.
Welcome to the second
lecture of CS25 this quarter.
And so today we're very lucky to
have two speakers here with us.
So Hazel or Heejeong Nam
is here in person today.
She's a master's student
at Brown University,
working on representation
learning, causality,
and self-supervised learning.
And we also have Lucas
Maes over Zoom, who
will be speaking afterwards.
And he's a PhD student at Mila
and the University of Montreal,
working on JEPA and planning.
So I'm sure they're going to
give us very insightful talk
today.
And so without further ado,
I'll hand it off to Hazel.
Yeah.
Thank you for introducing.
Hazel, first year master's
student in Brown University,
working with Professor
Randall Balestriero.
Our lab is working on JEPA,
self-supervised learning,
and some theory as well.
I'm a bit nervous.
This is my first time
giving a talk in English,
but at the same time,
I'm really, really
excited to talk about JEPA
world model and my recent work,
causal world model.
I'm pretty sure Lucas
is also very excited
to share his very recent
work, LeWorldModel.
OK.
So the first part
of this talk will
be about the concepts
of JEPA and world model.
And after a brief introduction
of those two concepts,
we will talk about the
Causal-JEPA paper first,
which gives a question about
how to make a model understand
the object interaction.
And then I will
hand over to Lucas,
and he will talk
about LeWorldModel.
And LeWorldModel is about
the end-to-end JEPA training
without collapse.
So first of all, I
think most of you guys
may have heard of world
model, and some of you guys
may be really familiar with
what is the world model.
To talk about the world model--
we should have this first.
So this is autoregressive model.
You get the previous state,
and you predict the next step.
However, this is sometimes not
enough to describe the world.
Why?
Because our world
has uncertainty.
At that time that
you're observing,
someone might do
something at that time.
Someone can throw something.
There's inherent uncertainty.
To handle this,
you need an action.
And this now is a world model.
So the world model
basically is a function
that gets the previous
state and the action
to predict the next state.
And in this sense, I perceive
the world model terminology
as a simulator.
So as an AI researcher,
what would you
do to make this
world model better?
In my opinion, I think
three points of designing.
The first one is having a
good state representation.
This is about-- so
you probably are not
going to give the raw pixel
images or raw pixel values
to the predictor.
You somehow have to have
a good representation that
reflects the world faithfully.
And the second component will
be a good transition model.
For example, there should
be a grounding rule
underlying the environment.
For example, there's
a gravity that exists.
We have to understand these
rules to predict the world
and to simulate the world.
And the last component is
the good dynamics model.
Now you're going
to do some action.
And your model should
react to your action
in the appropriate way.
Keep these three things
in mind because I'll
revisit this, end of
the Causal-JEPA part,
to discuss how I address
these three questions.
Today, we will not cover
generative world models.
There's so many industries now
are doing the world modeling
stuff.
For example, GAIA is an
autonomous driving model
that gets the action
in the previous state
to predict the next
driving scenario.
And the Genie, they want to
scaling up the world model,
so they learned something
called latent action, which
is a proxy of the
action, because usually
online data doesn't have the
per frame action annotation.
And Sora is a technically
video generation model.
But their fidelity of their
generated scene is very good,
so they got a lot of notice.
And Marble from Professor
Fei-Fei Li and Stanford.
They are doing the 3D
interactive environment so that
we can interact or explore.
But today, we will talk about
Joint-Embedding Predictive
Architecture, which is somewhat
different from the generative
world model.
So on the left side,
the thing you see
is generative world model,
because as you can see,
the x is the current state.
And let's say the y is the
thing that we have to predict,
which is like a future state.
You put the encoded current
set to the predictor,
and you directly
compare to y, which
means that your model should
give the same, the pixel space,
as your target is.
However, in the right side,
that is a Joint Predictive
Architecture.
You see both x and y are
going to the encoder.
So now we are comparing our
prediction and the true target
in the latent space.
So why does it matter?
We don't have decoder in
the JEPA architecture.
But it is not merely
about having no decoder.
It is about uncertainty
in the world.
So when human is thinking about
what is going to happen next,
are you predicting something
in a very pixel level,
there's some kind of uncertainty
that you cannot predict.
And there's obviously
like your interest in--
your area of interest.
So JEPA tries to deal with only
having predictive information
in your latent space so that
your prediction is getting more
meaningful and human-like way.
And also, the framework can be
interpreted in a different way.
First of all, the
generative world modeling
is about a likelihood.
They learn the
normalized likelihood
over the future frames.
But JEPA can be understood
as an energy-based model.
So in the very original paper
that Yann LeCun suggested,
he framed the JEPA as
an energy-based model.
And energy-based model learns
the energy score function
that gives the high value if two
values x and y are incompatible.
And they give low score
if those are compatible.
And compatibility in the world
model makes the point of the y
is a plausible future of x
So the energy-based model
can collapse, unfortunately.
And there's two ways to
prevent this collapse.
The first way is
contrastive learning.
And the second way is
regularization-based method.
I'm not going to talk
about this too deeply,
but the
regularization-based method
are making very rich and
well-defined energy landscape.
So that is what JEPA is doing.
For example, V-JEPA,
which is Video-JEPA,
they took on an input as
the consecutive frames
with the spatiotemporal masking.
And they put this encoder, and
they get the representation.
And they try to predict what is
happening in the unseen area.
So the target has
every information.
And here, there's some
regularization tool
to prevent collapse.
For example, they
use EMA encoder.
EMA here means Exponential
Moving Average.
This prevents like
really trivial collapses.
And also, you do stop gradient
for the target encoder,
and you put the mask to give
a model more challenging task.
V-JEPA 2 is basically the
same architecture as V-JEPA 1,
but they wanted to scale up.
And they also did some
interesting post-training.
And one of them is
action-conditioned control.
So now this became
more like word model
because now it's getting-- as
you can see in the predictor,
it gets the robot
action and poses.
So this is one of the
post-training in the V-JEPA 2.
And this is actually
called DINO World Model
and have a very
same architecture
as the action-conditioned
post-training that you just saw.
So what the DINO
World Model is doing
is they use the
frozen DINOv2 encoder.
What they claim is,
oh, do we actually
have to train the
JEPA encoder to get
the meaningful
abstraction for planning?
They said, no, a
pretrained DINO encoder
can do that role as well.
So they generate
patch representation.
And with the auxiliary
variable, for example, action
and proprioceptive signals,
they predict the future state
representation,
and they compare.
And this predictor is just
a simple Causal Transformer,
which predicts the
future autoregressively.
But here I want
you to think about,
is the past representation
is what really humans do?
Are we patchifying the image
to predict the next step?
Probably not.
So today, we're going to
talk about Causal-JEPA,
Learning World Models
through Object-Centric Latent
Interventions.
Before starting
this talk, I would
like to thank you for my
collaborators, Quentin, Lucas,
and Yann LeCun, and
Randall Balestriero.
So the goal of
the Causal-JEPA is
understanding the object
interaction and object dynamics.
These are three data sets
that I picked to show today.
The first one is Push-T,
a pretty famous example
in the control experiments.
The goal is you do
action on the blue ball,
and you want to move the
gray T block to perfectly
overlap on the green T.
And the second data
set is CLEVRER.
This is actually the
video paired with question
answering the data set.
The question is like--
it can be predictory.
For example, what would
happen in the next frame?
And it can be counterfactual.
For example, what would
happen if the blue color
cylinder doesn't exist?
And it can be explanatory.
So it's basically VQA benchmark.
And the third one is PHYRE.
As you can see, many objects
are interacting each other
with the grounding rule.
For example, there's a gravity.
The mass matters
here and et cetera.
So to understand
this object dynamics,
what the current models
are doing is like this.
They patchify the
image, and they
try to predict what will
happen in each patches.
But what are you going
to do to understand
this mechanism is you want to
understand the things like this.
You have each
object and you want
to know how one object
influences each other.
So what if in the DINO World
Model, what if you just
change the representation in the
object-centric representation?
Then it's more close to
human-like thinking, right?
But then we have to learn the
object-centric representation.
I'm not going to do
very deeply about
the object-centric learning,
but let me go through briefly.
If you're doing
computer vision, you
might have heard about the
object-centric learning.
There's a very foundational
way called slot attention
from Locatello.
This is basically
encoder-decoder framework.
And between this
encoder and decoder,
you might have the
feature space, right?
And you bring like a
bucket, like a basket,
to put each features.
And this basket is
for each object.
So there's a mechanism
called slot attention that
puts each feature to each slot.
So there's a binding
problem of feature to slot.
And they decode
with this basket so
that the model can have
well-aligned information
with the slots.
You don't have to read this
all, but I brought this
because this is United
Transformers class.
And slot attention is
about self-attention.
So what I want to show is--
how to bind the
features to the slot
is you do self-attention, where
key is the input features.
For example, in the DINOv2,
there's a patch embeddings.
You allocate each patch
embedding to slots.
You're basically assigning them.
And the value is also
the input features.
And you update the
slot by using GRU.
So you iteratively
update the slots.
And now the slot will have the
object-aligned representation.
So this is how usually
the models are getting
object-centric representation.
This is very, very
naive approaches.
There's so many advanced ways.
For example, this is for
image, and there's a video slot
attention models as well.
So yeah, you can give it a try.
And why does the model
behave if it perfectly
understands the dynamics?
Let's say the model learned
the monkey eating banana.
If model is truly understanding
this eating mechanism,
the model might be able to infer
what is happening to banana
when we cover the
invisible cloth on banana.
So even though you're
not seeing the banana,
if you see a monkey moving
their mouth constantly,
you can imagine, oh, a
banana might get shorter.
And vice versa, if you make
the monkey invisible and banana
is disappearing, you
can infer that a monkey
is eating something.
This is very core
motivation and very core
explanation of Causal-JEPA.
This is really relevant of
what I'm doing right now.
And if you think of
the previous example,
it doesn't have to be--
the predictor doesn't
have to be Causal Transformer.
As far as we are seeing
the only history,
we're OK to use multiple
time-step history.
So we're using a bidirectional
transformer here.
I would like to mention that.
And let's see how
the model actually
implements this, the monkey
and banana mechanism,
in the transformer.
Let's say we have
a nicely aligned
representation for each object.
And we include these object
states to the representation.
For example, let's say our
lookback history is four frames.
So you see four frames.
And next frame
prediction will happen.
But because this is not a causal
autoregressive transformer,
this is a bidirectional
ViT-style transformer,
we need a placeholder for
this future tokens as well.
So we use this as
a masked token.
And now so our goal is predict
this masked token correctly.
And for example, each row means
the evolution of each object.
Now, as I told you before,
I want to mask something.
Here, blue dots are
observable slots,
and the yellow one
is masked slot.
And let's imagine that we
have this masked slot here.
What should model do?
What is the easiest
way for model
to have a reasonably low
loss and just predict
the masked token?
Maybe just average the
previous and the next token,
just like doing interpolation.
But that is what we want.
What we want is like a learn
the object interaction.
So like the previous example of
monkey, I just mask everything.
This is a bit aggressive
way of masking.
But now the model
doesn't have shortcut.
It needs to infer the other
slots to correctly infer
the current state
or the masked state.
But what if we want to mask
two objects at the same time?
This can happen, because
in slot attention,
you have to fix the
maximum number of slots.
The number of slots doesn't
vary during training,
so you give plenty amount of
slot to give a model freedom OK,
what information should
define as a slot?
And sometimes in the scene--
for example, we
define eight slots,
but we only have three
objects in the scene.
Then just masking
only one object,
only one slot might
not be enough.
And then now we want to
put this into transformer.
And we have deflection, so we
have to do positional encoding
before then.
OK, there's no problem by
temporal positional encoding.
But when we are trying to do
positional encoding in the slot
axis, there's a problem, because
what object-centric models are
doing is they do not define
the order of the objects,
but rather the object-centric
models are permutationally
equivalent depends with
respect to the object orders.
So this is basically not
list but set of objects.
And then if you are
masking multiple objects,
the model might not
know what to predict,
because these slots are
not having object identity.
So the video slot attentions can
keep the temporal consistency
inside the video itself.
For example, Video A
have the consistency
with the object order.
But we cannot guarantee that
Video A and Video B are having
the same order of objects.
So now what we do is we do not
mask the very first time step.
In this case, time
step t minus 3.
And we use this information
as a slot identity.
And what we are
doing is we define
each masked token with the
identity token plus learnable
masked token with the
positional encoding.
And this is less
aggressive because you
have an initial
condition of each object.
So it makes more sense when
you predict the masked tokens.
And the other part
I want to talk about
is action conditioning.
The world model should condition
on the action properly.
And what the DINO
World Model is doing
is they concatenate the action
embedding behind the patch
embedding.
For example, DINOv2-Small has
384 dimension of the features.
And let's say we have 10
dimensional action embedding.
And what DINO World Model
do is they duplicate
it to make the number
of the patches,
and they just put
the action embedding
after the patch representation.
So now it's like 894
per patch because we
added this action embedding
after the patch representation.
But this is not really
optimal way, I think,
because what we want to
learn is something like this.
Why don't we consider action
as another node of the graph?
The Causal-JEPA does not
recover any true causal graph,
but its motivation is
grounded in the causal graph.
So for example, because
we define each object
representation, those are
playing a role of the nodes.
And we also try to use this
action as one of the node.
So in this current
situation, the action
is added like
something like this,
not as a part of the
feature representation.
So this is the architecture
of the Causal-JEPA.
So to sum up, you have
the history frames.
And you put this into the
object-centric encoder
to get the object
representation.
And then you select some
amount of objects to mask,
and you mask it.
And you put this
into predictor, which
is bidirectional
transformer with the action.
And then you're predicting
every masked tokens.
And now we will
see some results.
I did three experiments
based on our goal.
Our goal is understanding
the object dynamics.
And the first thing is reasoning
on the counterfactual questions.
And the second thing is
planning and control.
And third is physical
implausibility.
So in the CLEVRER,
we did an experiment
with the other existing
models as well.
But what I want to highlight
is the model without masking.
What I want to say
here is the performance
is not because we use the
object-centric representation,
but the core is masking,
like in the banana example.
So if you see the C-JEPA result,
not only average accuracy
is better.
You can see there's
a clearly clear gain
in the counterfactual question.
This counterfactual
question is very well
resonated with our
original motivation
because the counterfactual
is asking something like,
oh, what if this
object doesn't exist?
What if this object exists?
Something like this.
So you have to understand how
the object interact each other.
And the next example
is Push-T planning.
The agent tried to control the
object to reach the goal state.
And here I want to
emphasize the efficiency.
If you can see the DINO
World Model baseline,
you have 196 patches, if you
imagine you are having 2 to 4
by 2 to 4 images.
And each patch should have a
384 dimension of the features.
And if you're using
object-centric representation,
the number of tokens are
significantly less than that.
And because now we have the
clear semantic from each token,
the feature doesn't
have to be super large.
If you think of--
there's nothing much
to include in the object.
For example, texture. color,
shape, rotational state,
and location.
That's not that much.
We don't need like a really
huge representation space.
So after we only put in
object-centric representation
instead of the
patch representation
in the DINO World
Model, its performance
actually drops a lot.
And this can be true
because DINO World Model
used the causal transformer.
And we use bidirectional
transformer, right?
And the object-centered
representation if you think
of doesn't necessarily have
to include the velocity
or acceleration stuff, because
you cannot define those
properties by only looking
at the single static image.
So this drops the
performance a lot.
And after we changed the
action-conditioning method,
treating them as
a separated node,
and we change the transformer to
the bidirectional transformer,
the performance
gain is significant.
It gains this 15% of
absolute percentages.
And after masking, compared
to the OC, Object-Centric DINO
World Model, you gain 28%,
which is pretty large.
And compared to the
OC-JEPA, the only difference
is object masking.
And this object masking
actually helps the model
to understand these dynamics.
And this is the effect of
the action conditioning.
As I told you before, the latent
concatenation in the red line
denotes the
action-conditioning method
based on the DINO World Model.
But after we treating this
action as a separated node,
it clearly shows the margin.
And there's an additional
experiment on PHYRE.
PHYRE is-- among three
data sets we have,
it's like most
complicated dynamics.
And there's a lot of
formulation configuration.
And you need to
learn precisely what
is happening in the scenario.
And when I compare the
OC-JEPA and C-JEPA,
OC-JEPA often generates some
physically implausible scene.
You see like the bar is
floating below the fixed
bar, which doesn't make sense.
And this can be done by
just learning correlation.
When two bars are closed,
they just stay there.
But that's not true.
That's not how physics works.
So by the training
method of object masking,
you keep asking the question
to the model, what would
happen if this doesn't exist?
What should you consider to
predict the masked token?
It can learn the true dynamics.
And this is the
attention probing
for this previous example.
You can see the
failure is actually
coming from attending to
the wrong irrelevant object.
So for example, OC-JEPA
relies on the cup, which
contains the blue ball,
and the C-JEPA conditioned
on the right bar to
predict its future state.
And here, the Causal-JEPA,
the terminology causal can--
it can sense for many things.
But here, we use the causal
as a temporally directed
predictive dependencies,
which means
that because we're predicting
the future from the history,
the edge is directed.
And to predict the
masked token, you
need to attend to
the relevant object.
So we call it
temporally directed
predictive dependencies.
This is not the very
conventional and traditional way
of defining causal, but recent
modern causal machine learning
is this kind of
definition as well.
And here, to go back to the
role of the object masking,
we say this predictor finds
influence neighborhood.
Influence neighborhood--
we just define its name.
But it's just a
predictably sufficient set.
So it's like a
minimal set that it
needs to predict the
masked token correctly.
And this can be true.
More formally, this can
be true for assumptions.
The first thing is we
do not assume there's
an instantaneous relationship.
And the second assumption is
that every training instances
should share the same mechanism.
For example, the gravity
should not change along videos.
There's a governing rule
applied in the whole data set.
And the third assumption is
object-aligned representation.
This is the most tricky
in the practical sense,
because this assumes that our
object-centric representation is
constant throughout the video.
It should not getting swapped.
The object should not be split
into the different slots.
And our representation should
reflect the scenario faithfully.
And the fourth is
history sufficiency.
This is because we
use finite history.
For example, we see
four previous frames
and predict the next frame.
And this four history
frame should be
enough to predict the future.
And to make this causal
machine learning to practical,
we do not assume
first-order Markov process.
As I told before, the
object-centric representation
usually does not follow the
first-order Markov process.
And we allow confounder.
The confounder makes things
really tricky because we cannot
recover the true
causal graph usually
because of the confounder.
But in the object-centric
representation
in the real world,
this is inevitable.
So I would like to answer
this questions really quickly.
What happens if object-centric
representation is not faithful?
A little bit is fine because
still, masking object slots
is still some kind
of inductive bias,
even though our
masking is not perfect.
So a little minor--
like the wrong model can be
OK, but if it's really bad,
it doesn't work.
Is there any way to recover
the true causal graph?
No in our method.
There's confounders, so we
cannot recover the true causal
graph.
And also, sometimes
it's really hard
to define what is the true
causal graph in many scenarios.
How to select the number
of objects to mask?
This is a good question, because
we have a fixed number of slots,
and the number of actual objects
are varying depend on which
frame are we looking at.
The ideal amount is just
only one foreground object
without the background slots.
But we sometimes cannot
control this really well,
so I would say decide the number
of masks based on the data
statistics.
Just guess your perfect
number of the mask.
And you should sweep a bit
to find the perfect number.
And the limitation--
the largest limitation
is coming from the
object-centric encoder.
The object-centric
representation
does not work really well
on the occlusion situation.
And, in the middle of
the video, some objects
can appear and disappear.
But this slot attention cannot
handle this scenario really
well.
So this is some pain
point of this model.
And finally, we got back to this
three components of world model
again.
In the beginning
of the talk, I said
there's a three component
that we should consider
to make a good world model.
And for the good
state representation,
we use this object
representation.
And for a good
transition model, we
did object masking to
let the model learn
the predictive sufficiency.
And about the dynamics
model, we tweak the method
to condition the action.
So we treat this action
variables as a separated node.
I think this is all of
the Causal-JEPA part.
And let me quickly put to Lucas.
So hi, everyone.
My name is Lucas.
I'm a third year
PhD student at Mila,
advised by Damien Scieur,
who is researcher in Samsung.
But I work closely with
Randall Balestriero,
who is prof at Brown.
And the work I'm going
to talk about today
is the work I done in
collaboration with Quentin Le
Lidec, who is postdoc at NYU;
with Yann LeCun, Damien; Yann
LeCun and Randall.
So today, what I'm going
to talk about briefly
is how to make this whole
world model stuff and JEPA
stuff pretty simple to train.
And I'm not going to tell you
again what is the world model.
I think Hazel did
it pretty well.
So I'm going to go
directly to what we did.
So just before
that, I would like
to talk about a big problem.
So as Hazel say, JEPA aim
to learn representation
in abstract space.
And so it's directly
in opposition
to generative modeling,
wherein generative modeling,
what we try to do is you try
to model your input space.
Basically, you try to learn a
representation of your input
space and try to do stuff in
your input pace-- input space,
sorry.
And so JEPA say that this
is for most of your tasks,
not desirable.
For instance, if you do
self-driving car application,
you most likely
don't care to model
the movement of the leaf
of the tree in the road.
You don't care to model that.
If you do generative
modeling, by definition,
you will have to model that
because you want to model
all the detail of your input.
So your loss is going
to give signal for that.
So what JEPA propose is to
first encode all your input
into an abstract
space, typically
with an encoder or
neural net, and then
try to model the dynamic--
the dynamics-- sorry-- of your
space in that latent space.
So it's pretty nice
when you say like that.
But if you look on the
right the image I put,
if you just do that, you suffer
from what people call collapse.
And so what is collapse?
It's a failure mode where you
can see that if I do nothing,
I don't put constraint on the
distribution of my embeddings,
your model on the
right can simply
learn to disregard the input and
just produce a constant vector.
And so you can minimize the
prediction loss in the latent
space just by saying, OK, I
am going to encode everything
as a constant vector like 0.
And then it's trivially
easy to predict
what is going to be the next--
state is going to
just be 0 again.
And so the whole
research on JEPA--
a big part of the
research on JEPA
is how do you avoid
that collapse.
So as Hazel said
before, I should
add a Causal-JEPA in that
previous JEPA recipe as well.
You have V-JEPA that try to do--
that try to avoid that collapse
with exponential moving average.
You have DINO World Model
that uses a pretrained encoder
basically to avoid the
collapse, because if you
use a pretrained encoder
and you froze it,
you can produce
nontrivial embedding,
and you can learn the dynamics
directly in the embedding.
So it's essentially supervised
learning in our model.
And then you have PLDM that
try everything end to end.
So they train the encoder or
the predictor and everything end
to end and their
action-conditioned model
as well.
But they use something
called VICReg.
And what is VICReg?
It's just an anti-collapse
regularization term
that try to make the covariance
matrix of your features,
of your latent
feature's identity.
So basically, you
want each dimension
to be decorrelated from the
other of your feature space,
except for the
covariance matrix.
The diagonal line
is one typically.
So you have a
positive correlation.
The problem with
PLDM is as you--
as you can see on the
slide, you need to apply.
So one term for the variance.
One term for the
covariance minimization.
You need to do that
spatially and temporally.
So you have four terms.
They add an additional
inverse dynamics
loss to try to gain more
information about the action,
whatever.
It's 5.
Plus, you have the
prediction in the future.
The L2 minimization
you see on the right.
So your predictor try to predict
the future in the latent space.
And you compare that with
what your encoder say
about the future should be.
And so it gives you
a six-term loss,
so it's pretty difficult to
tune that because you have
six hyperparameters to tune.
And that's why we
propose LeWorldModel.
So what is LeWorldModel?
It's just a simple JEPA
that doesn't use any tricks.
So there is no Exponential
Moving Average, no masking,
no stop gradient, no
pretrained encoder,
and also no unstable loss.
Why?
Because we have a
single hyperparameter.
And we make the model such that
it's only 16 million parameter.
So it means you can train
that on a single GPU.
It's fully end to
end from raw pixels,
so there is no
auxiliary information
such as proprioception
information or whatever.
And we observe that
it's 50 times faster
than the LeWorldModel
for doing planning.
So basically, what
is LeWorldModel?
It's basically JEPA
in its pure essence.
So what you do is you
take an observation ot,
an observation ot plus 1,
so the next observation.
You process-- [COUGHS]
sorry.
You process both of them
through a shared encoder.
And you get a representation
zt and zt plus 1.
What you're going
to do in the task
is you will use zt and
the action at step t
and try to learn a predictor
to model the dynamics.
So you're going to try
to predict the future.
So you have an estimation of
the future called zt plus 1.
And you compare that
to what your encoder
predict for the next state.
You use Mean Squared
Error, and you
use what we call SIGReg
to avoid collapse.
What is nice is
that basically what
I told you about before with
JEPA is literally what you see.
And the code is exactly
what I just described.
So if you look at the
pseudocode on the right,
it's actually not
that much pseudocode.
It's literally the true code.
You encode.
You predict.
You compute your prediction,
your future prediction error.
And you use SIGReg
to avoid collapse.
So you can see that at the
bottom line at the return,
I have a single
hyperparameter lambda.
So this is the only
stuff you need to tune.
And because you have a
single hyperparameter,
you can do a bisection.
So it's log n to find
the optimal lambda.
So it's pretty nice
because we can really
easily tune the model.
And so what is SIGReg now?
So this is the stuff that avoids
your representation collapse
and make sure that your zt or--
informative about what is
inside your observation.
So basically, you
can see zt as learned
abstraction of the world
or a learned state.
You have an observation of the
world, which is the image ot.
And you try to learn-- you
try to estimate the state,
the ground-truth state.
And so how do you
prevent collapse?
Basically, we use a
simple regularization
called SIGReg or Sketched
Isotropic Gaussian Regularizer
that Randall and Yann LeCun
introduced last November,
I think, if I'm correct.
And the idea is very simple.
The math are a bit tricky, but
I invite you to read the paper.
It's a very nice paper.
But the idea is very simple.
You take the distribution
of your embedding.
So you take your batch.
You look at how your
embedding zt distributed.
And you will try to
optimize that distribution
to be isotropic Gaussian.
So how do you do that?
You could use
generative modeling
to do that with the KL
divergence and everything,
such as Variational Autoencoder.
We don't want that here.
We don't want to use
generative models.
So what you do is
you're going to try
to use a statistical test.
So in statistics,
you have tests that
tells you given an empirical
distribution, how close it--
how close is it to
Gaussian distribution?
The problem is that
our embedding space
is very high-dimensional.
And so there is no test that--
basically, the
statistical test, they
suffer from the curse
of dimensionality,
so it's very difficult
to directly use
a test to optimize in
high-dimensional distribution.
And so what Randall had--
our idea is to
basically project.
You sample a lot of random
direction in your latent space,
and you're going to
project all your embedding
into one dimension.
So as you can see,
for instance, if you
look at the red arrow on this
image and you look on the right,
you can see that once you
project your embedding
into that direction, you get a
unimodal-- sorry, a univariate
empirical distribution.
And now you can optimize because
it's just a 1D distribution.
You can optimize to
make that Gaussian.
And if you do that--
in a lot of directions,
there is a theorem called
Cramér--Wold theorem that says
that if you optimize the
marginals to be Gaussian,
then the joint is
going to be Gaussian.
So basically, if you do that
for a lot of random direction,
you can prove that your latent
embedding distribution is
going to be Gaussian as well.
So it makes us sure that we
will have informative embedding.
So that's pretty nice.
OK, so now how can
you-- let's imagine
you train your world model,
blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
How can you make sure that
you learn a good world model?
So there is two ways.
I mean, I know two ways.
If you more than, that's nice.
We can talk about that.
But the first way
is online control.
So can you use your LeWorldModel
that is action-conditioned?
And can you in an online
way optimize this action
to perform control?
So this is the first thing.
And the second thing we are
going to talk about after is
try to assess if your
world model understand
intuitive physics.
But let's focus on
control for now.
So how we perform control is
basically we are going to--
with your model,
the LeWorldModel,
you're going to sample random
trajectories of action.
And you're going to optimize
by rolling out the future.
You will optimize that
sequence of action
to match a target goal.
So for instance, let's say
you have a goal frame Og.
You start from the
current frame O1.
You both encode them
through your encoder.
You got the initial
state, latent state Z1.
You have your target
state, which is zg.
And then you sample an
initial sequence of action.
And you use the first
one with your first state
inside the predictor.
It gives you z2.
Then you use the second one, et
cetera, blah, blah, blah, blah,
blah.
And after each state--
each step, sorry,
you compare how far
are you in your latent space to
the representation of the goal.
It can be MSE.
For instance, you
use the MSE loss
to estimate how far
you are from your goal.
And because your predictor
is differentiable,
you can for instance
backpropagate
until the action try to--
sequence of action to minimize
the distance with your goal.
So I can show you some results.
You can see that we
consider four tasks.
So the first one on the
left is called TwoRoom.
It's a simple 2D navigation task
where you need to move from one
side of a room into the other
by passing through a door.
Then you have Reacher.
It comes from DeepMind Control
Suite, where you need to--
you can see on the right
you have a 2D like--
sorry, a two-joint arm.
And you need to match a target
location from a given goal.
Then you have Push-T.
So Push-T is already present.
But the goal of Push-T is
to push basically the T
to the green area.
That's as simple as that.
And you can only push.
You cannot pull.
And OG-Bench Cube, it's a 3D
environment where the objective
of that environment
is to make the cube--
your cube, it's a 3D
manipulation robotic arm where
you need to make the cube
matching a target location
as well.
And so I think the most
interesting result is--
the first one is
Push-T, because you
can see that DINO
World Model has been
trained with proprioception.
And you can see
that LeWorldModel
without proprioception beat DINO
World Model with proprioception
with half the parameter.
But what is most
interesting is if you remove
the proprioception
of DINO World Model,
you see that the
performance drop.
And LeWorldModel, because it
doesn't have proprioception,
it beats by a lot
the LeWorldModel
without proprioception.
And PLDM, which is
the only other one
that doesn't use proprioception
and that is fully trained end
to end, also have very bad
performance on Push-T. So
it was very nice
to see this result.
So for Reacher, we beat PLDM
and DINO World Model as well.
But what is really interesting
is that for OG-Bench Cube,
for instance, we beat PLDM, but
we don't beat DINO World Model.
And the most likely
explanation for that
is that we only
train on trajectories
coming from the data sets.
But DINO World Model has
been pretrained because it's
a pretrained encoder.
It has been pretrained on
124 million natural images.
And consequently, it has a
better understanding about
objects and 3D than we have
because it has been trained
on a lot, lot, lot more data.
And also very funnily, you
can see that for TwoRoom,
even if it's the simplest
task, almost all the baseline
destroy the task.
But for us, we don't.
And this is actually
a limitation of SIGReg
that exists for now is f if you
have intrinsic dimensionality.
So what I mean by that is the
true dimensionality that you
need to solve the problem.
For instance, so
TwoRoom is just 2,
because you just need to
the x and y of the agent.
As soon as you know that and
I give you a target location,
you can solve the environment.
If that is very much smaller
than the embedding you use,
there is no way that you can
produce Gaussian embeddings.
At least your SIGReg
when you optimize
is going to need to create fake
stuff to be able to be Gaussian,
fake, like to use some
information to make your latent
space Gaussian.
So it doesn't help
you, basically.
There is research going
on to try to fix that.
And actually, we know
that if you carefully
tune the hyperparameter, you can
somewhat overcome this issue.
But for the sake of
fairness, we didn't hypertune
all the hyperparameters, and
we keep the same hyperparameter
across all the environment.
But the most interesting
part why it's very nice
is when you look at
the planning time.
So for DINO World
Model-- and we heavily
optimized DINO World Model to
try to be as fast as possible.
The fastest we could go
for doing the full planning
is 47 seconds.
And the reason for that
is because you need to--
your predictor takes
all the patches.
And you need to predict
all the patches,
so it's quite slow because
of the quadratic cost
of the attention to
predict the future.
As for us, with LeWorldModel,
we have a single embedding
for representing
the latent state
because we just use the
CLS token of the encoder.
And it allows us
some other tricks.
We didn't optimize
a lot for that.
We could go a lot
less than this.
But we can go to a
full playing time
under the second,
which is very nice.
It's almost 50 times faster.
Another thing interesting is
that if you fix the FLOP--
so if you fix the FLOP that
you used for planning--
and we fix the FLOP at
those of LeWorldModel.
So if you reduce
the planning time
by tweaking the hyperparameter
for the planning
until DINO World Model
plan under a second,
you can see that the success
rate drop by a lot for Push-T
and for OG-Bench Cube,
which is expected.
But it showed that
at similar budget,
we outperform even on OG-Bench
Cube DINO World Model.
So that's for the control.
For intuitive physics
understanding,
we did something pretty
similar-- pretty easy, sorry.
The first thing is we
probe the latent space.
So we just took the encoder from
LeWorldModel, and we froze it.
And we train a linear or
NLP probe, non-linear probe,
to try to predict the
coefficients of the simulation
for that state.
So I will not go that
much into the detail.
You can have a look
at the paper for that.
But what is pretty interesting
is that for instance,
for OG-Bench Cube, you can
see that the linear probe with
LeWorldModel, we almost all the
time have a lower mean squared
error, which means that--
if you compare with the
NLP probe on the right,
it's almost DINO World
Model all the time
that have the lowest
mean squared error.
And so what it suggests
is that our latent space
is less entangled than
one on DINO World Model.
So it's more easy to recover
the coefficient directly
from the latent space rather
than DINO World Model.
And it doesn't make
sense, I think,
because as we used SIGReg,
it pushed like the latent
space in such a way
where each dimension are
somewhat meaningless.
So it's not fully
disentangled, but it's
somewhat more than Dino World
Model, which is pretty nice.
Another thing that you could
do, which is pretty cool,
is to try to see what happens
when you violate the world
model.
So if a sudden change
in the dynamics happen,
does your world model predict
that this is a violation?
And so what we did
for that is, as you
can see on the left-- sorry,
the cube color and cube
teleportation are inverted.
But if you look on
the left, you can
see that we have a
normal trajectory where
your robotic arm pick up the
cube and move it to the right,
for instance, OK?
Nothing happened.
And then we consider
two perturbation.
For instance, we change
the color of the cube.
So this is the one on the
right, not in the middle.
Suddenly, at a given frame, OK?
And another transformation we
did is randomly, like suddenly--
this is the one in the
middle-- the cube teleport.
And so if you look
on the right, you
can see that the x-axis
are the time steps, OK?
And the y-axis is
the prediction error.
So this is the
difference between what
your predictor predict
is going to happen
and what the actual embedding of
the next states look like, OK?
And so what you can
see is that if you
don't have any perturbation--
so this is the gray line--
it's fine.
If you change the cube
color, it's a bit higher,
but it's very negligible.
So it means that basically your
world model don't care much
about the color
of the cube, which
is pretty cool because you don't
need that for the dynamics.
You don't care about
the color of the cube.
But if suddenly
the cube teleports,
then the prediction
error shoot a lot,
meaning that your world
model didn't predict that.
Some people say to
me often that yeah,
but it's just
out-of-distribution.
And I would say it's
true, but I think
it's not very meaningful to
say that because as human, when
you violate your model, it's
also very out-of-distribution.
That's why, for
instance, when someone
do to you a magic trick where
they make a coin disappear
in front of you, you're
suddenly very surprised,
and it frustrates you a bit.
It's the same here.
It's because the prediction
error is very high.
So we did two other small
experiments as well.
The first one is we try to
embed the location of the agent
and the T. And we try to make
the agent location and the T
location move.
So you can see that the middle
plot shows you what happened,
the different location.
And we try to project
with a t-SNE plot
the embedding space to try
to see if we can recover
this exact relative
distance between all
the different locations
of the original space.
And what you can see is
that up to a permutation
of the axis and reflection,
this is exactly what happened.
So we recover basically
the relative distance
in the original space,
which is pretty nice.
The last thing we did is
we froze the world model,
and we train a decoder to try to
interpret what is happening when
you make future prediction.
And so for that, you can
see that we give a context
to our world model.
So this is the first three
frame of the top row you see,
or the bottom, the
second row, OK?
So we give that to our model.
The first row is really
what happened in the future,
on the right, where you
have open-loop prediction.
So this is actually what
happened in the trajectory.
And then on the second row,
you have what your world model
imagine when you give the
same sequence of action that
has been taken for
the original sequence.
And you can see that
the world model predicts
somewhat the reality when you
give the sequence of action.
But what is very
interesting is that if you
look at the second
rollout with the cube--
so you can see that we
predict very well what is
going to happen with the cube.
But if you are very careful, you
can see that at frame 15 and 20,
the angle of the
gripper is opposite.
And so basically, you can see
that the world model didn't
learn the rotation
of the gripper, which
was pretty interesting, because
it still was able to solve
somewhat the environment.
So there is many
limitations for our model,
or as I like to call them,
research opportunities.
So for now, you are doomed to
short-term planning horizon.
So if you can unlock that,
that would be very nice.
Another problem is that you have
them at a single temporal level.
So we need
hierarchies, basically.
For instance, when
you think about oh, I
need to go to the airport, you
think at a different hierarchy.
The airport is your goal.
You think, OK, I
need to go to my car,
then I need to go to airport
and blah, blah, blah.
And then only at the end, it
translates into muscle movement.
So you don't all the time think
in terms of muscle movement.
So we need that as well to
be able to predict further
in the future.
A very important
stuff as well is
to move from this
toy environment.
I fully agree with
this kind of criticism,
that it's very
toy-ish experiments.
And so can we move to
real-world robotics
or very stochastic and
partially observable
environment like Minecraft.
That would be very nice.
And also, a big
problem I think is,
how do you specify your goal?
So for now, you can see,
as I explained before,
you need to provide a visual
goal, but you don't all the time
have access to that.
And it doesn't tell
you anything about how
you should solve the task.
So for instance, if you have
a plane that needs to land,
you don't want to just show
a picture of the plane landed
to do the planning.
You want to specify
how smooth should
be the landing and everything.
So we don't how to do that for
now with this kind of approach.
I would like also to
take just two minutes
to do a bit of advertisement for
something we have been pushing
with a lot of Randall's
students and a lot of people
for the past few months, which
is called stable-worldmodel.
And if you're interested
about world model
research and this kind of
stuff, you should definitely
have a look for that.
So it's a GitHub library,
fully open-source,
that allows you to train
very easily world models.
So you have all the baseline
I discussed about and Hazel
discuss about that are
implemented there and heavily
tested.
You have all solver
to do planning.
You have many environments.
We recently added DeepMind
Control and Minecraft.
And we are in discussion to add
support for real robot data also
very soon.
And everything is
very heavily tested,
and there is documentation.
So yeah, feel free to give a try
and give feedback or contribute
to library.
That would be very cool.
Thank you.
OK, great.
Thank you so much.
Let's give a round of applause
to our speakers today.
[APPLAUSE]
So now we'll be
soliciting some questions.
We have some online on
Slido, but I'll also
be looking for in-person
questions in case anybody
here wants to ask
anything as well.
So we'll balance between both.
And I'll let you guys figure out
who should answer each question.
Or if you both have insights
for anything, that's also great.
Yeah, does anybody here
have any questions?
Well, I'm just curious
how does the world model
transfer to physical AI space?
How can we see them moving
forward in robotic space?
I would give it to
Lucas, probably.
Lucas, can you hear us?
Yes, yes.
Can you repeat the
question, please?
Oh.
So how can we expect the world
models in the physical AI space?
Because we already have a
diffusion-based foundation
models like GR00T or maybe
pi, and also Psi-Zero.
Using world models, can we
expect some more applications
in the robotics space?
OK, OK, OK.
So first of all, I
will be very skeptical
that the current VLA models
have a good understanding
of the world.
There is no reason for that.
They are not trained to predict
the consequence of their action,
OK?
And I will be very
skeptical to see something
that doesn't know what is
the outcome of his action,
be very reliable
to the physical AI.
So as human, why you are
very good at what you do
is because you can
predict what is
the consequence of your
action in the real world.
And that's what world
model try to do.
VLA don't do that.
So if you want to
have physical AI,
basically, you need world model.
You cannot bypass that.
I think, as Yann say, often
like VLA and everything,
they can be very
helpful for simple stuff
where you don't
need to predict what
is going to be the outcome of
your action in the real world.
For instance, if you want
to make robots that--
I don't know-- do some dance
or whatever, they only need
to their internal dynamics, OK?
They don't need how to
interact with the real world.
To interact with
the real world, you
need to predict the
outcome of your action,
so you need world models.
I hope that answers
your question.
If not, happy to clarify.
Sure, sure.
Thank you.
I would like to answer
one more sentence.
I think Professor
Sherry Yang in NYU,
she has an opinion
that world model can
be an evaluator for policies.
So I think this can
be also your answer.
Yeah.
We have someone at Slido.
Let me see.
Someone's asking, masking is
shown to improve predictions,
but is it really necessary
to learn the world model?
Does it mean that prediction
loss alone is insufficient?
The prediction loss--
OK, let me assume
that you're talking
about-- you're
still talking about the
object-centric representation.
If you only do the
prediction loss
with no object-centric
representation, the shortcut
or what model we learn is
it can be the self-dynamics.
We cannot guarantee
that the model learns
the interaction-based dynamics.
So I won't say that
it's insufficient,
but with the masking, I think
you can reinforce the model
to learn the object dynamics.
Yeah, that makes sense.
Someone's asking, do
you have any insights
on how C-JEPA
learns to plan ahead
beyond just the next frame?
So for the-- is it
all of the question?
Yeah.
OK.
We strictly follow
the evaluation method.
I mean, the planning of
the DINO World Model.
So with the predicted
future frame,
we do with autoregressively to
reach the long-horizon planning.
And we use the same, the
parameters for planning as well.
Any in-person questions?
OK, I'll continue
with the online ones
because we have quite a lot.
Let me see.
Someone's asking, what would a
JEPA native agent architecture
look like compared to
current LLM-based agents?
Lucas, do you want to answer?
Of course.
Can you just repeat
the question?
It's pretty difficult to hear.
Someone asked, what would a
JEPA native agent architecture
look like compared to
current LLM-based agents?
OK.
Basically, the way it
differs is that you
learn action-conditioned
model, right?
So LLM agent, you don't learn
action-conditioned model,
as far as I know.
I'm not expert in LLM as well.
But you learn to use tooling
and to make tool calls.
This is not what you do
when you do world models.
What you do is you learn,
OK, I have an action.
I am a current state.
What is going to happen in the
future if I take that action?
This is not how you train LLMs.
So this is one
step that differs.
And the second thing is that
by construction, you can just
learn to model the
future with world models
and then use planning by using
old concept of control theory,
such as model predictive
control or whatever,
to directly convert
that into an agent.
You don't need
post-training or whatever.
You can do that zero-shot.
So that's pretty neat.
For LLM, I'm not sure, so
I cannot reply for that.
I think that makes sense.
Yeah.
I guess this is--
let me see.
Yeah, do you think JEPA models
are less prone to hallucination
than transformer-based
models, since they hopefully
learn a more accurate
representation of the world?
I'm not sure if you guys
might have any insights.
I can answer first.
And, Lucas, you can just
add your opinion on it.
I'm not sure what kind of
hallucination the person asked,
but in the predictive sense,
because JEPA model is--
as I mentioned earlier
part of the talk,
the JEPA is energy-based model.
So rather than just predicting
the full pixel space, what
it evaluate is oh, is our
predicted future make sense?
Is it a possible situation,
or is it impossible?
So I think in that sense, in
the sense of the representation,
the representation will be
more suitable for world model,
I think.
Yeah.
Yeah, so I can complete on that.
So I think the
original question was
to compare JEPA and
transformer-based model.
So I would like
just to emphasize
that JEPA is not
an architecture,
a new architecture.
For instance, for
LeWorldModel, [INAUDIBLE]
encoder and predictor
are two transformers.
So JEPA is really a framework
to try to learn world model.
It's not a new architecture.
And second, I think you can
have definitely a hallucination
if you don't learn a good model.
But this is not at all
the same hallucination
as you have with LLM, because
LLM, they have multiple sources
from hallucination.
One of them is that they are not
grounded in the real world, OK?
With world model, you
can easily fix that.
Additionally, also, you can
say that with world model,
you can have another
source of hallucination
as well is that when
you optimize the action
sequence that you want
to do for doing planning,
you could have
actions that are not
meaningful for the real world.
For instance, let's say
that your action is minus.
It's between minus 1 and 1,
and that your optimizer say,
OK, you should use
minus 2 as an action.
So you can have this
kind of hallucination.
Otherwise, it's just about the
quality of your learned model.
And this is just a matter
of data and capacity.
Hopefully, that makes sense.
Yeah, no, great.
I think that makes
a lot of sense.
Thanks.
We have someone asking,
are world models
better than the diffusion-based
models for robot control?
I think we would have similar
answer as the previous one.
The world model can still
use the diffusion model.
Yeah, of course, of course.
You could use diffusion
model to train JEPA.
Actually, some people
try to do that.
Diffusion model have some
advantage and some limitation
as well.
So yeah.
Any in-person questions?
All right.
We got one at the back.
A longer horizon question.
But you mentioned that you
might consider planning
through this whole family of
different algorithms developed
for control, like model
predictive control, et cetera.
And you mentioned
that it might be
possible to use these
things as a grounding signal
to train policies.
Do you think that it's
combining those approaches,
if maybe that's what you already
meant by training policies,
though, of turning
up a lot of compute
on something like an alternative
controller for a relatively
long horizon, and
then distilling those
back down into policies might
be an efficient way of getting
some longer horizon behavior
for one of those problems
and/or research
directions you mentioned?
You want to go for
it, Hazel, or--
You can go for it.
OK.
Yeah, you can definitely
train a policy
on that, because as soon as you
have world model, basically,
you can do either two things.
You can use that directly and
optimize your action sequence
to have a zero-shot policy.
Or you can do the same
as Dreamer, for instance,
and use your pretrained world
model and train reinforcement
learning policy on
that, and periodically
go in your environment,
and collect better data
and fine-tune your model,
improve your policy,
and blah, blah, blah.
You can do that as well.
So in the future,
I think you will
have something similar to System
1, System 2, same as human does,
where you will have basically
an action-reaction policy, where
you will learn to
directly predict
what is the action I should
take to have that goal given
this state.
And then for difficult
tasks that you are not
very confident about
planning and model predictive
control to have more
careful plan and situation.
For instance, when you want
to learn to drive a car, maybe
at the first 20 hours, you will
use model predictive control
to make sure you
don't kill someone.
And then after 20 hours,
you think you are an expert.
So you can basically
distill your prediction
of model predictive
control and planning
to a direct policy that
outputs directly the action.
All right.
Great.
Unfortunately, that's
all the time we have.
Hazel will be staying after in
case anybody has any questions
or wants to talk to her.
So thanks again to our speakers
for the very insightful talk.
Thank you.